<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>SimoneMessaggi.it - Music</title><link href="https://www.simonemessaggi.it/" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://www.simonemessaggi.it/feeds/music.atom.xml" rel="self"/><id>https://www.simonemessaggi.it/</id><updated>2025-09-06T00:00:00+02:00</updated><subtitle>Learn the most from the worst</subtitle><entry><title>Artec POA4, get pro tone on your p-bass for 27 euros!</title><link href="https://www.simonemessaggi.it/2025/09/en/artec-poa4-pro-tone-precision-bass-27-euros/" rel="alternate"/><published>2025-09-06T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2025-09-06T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>simmessa</name></author><id>tag:www.simonemessaggi.it,2025-09-06:/2025/09/en/artec-poa4-pro-tone-precision-bass-27-euros/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Are you stuck on a bass that is a blast to play but has a bad sound? Here's a quick test and the resulting experience of upgrading the stock pickups to the Artec POA4 Precision bass pickups for an HB DIY bass kit I built. The difference with the stock …&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Are you stuck on a bass that is a blast to play but has a bad sound? Here's a quick test and the resulting experience of upgrading the stock pickups to the Artec POA4 Precision bass pickups for an HB DIY bass kit I built. The difference with the stock pickups is very detectable, in my opinion, but the newer pickups come with their own issue... Luckily, it's an easy fix! Check out the video for sound samples, my opinions and a before / after comparison of the bass sound.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="315" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/IXKsPk_UORQ?si=TgulNkEDwJx8jQX_" title="YouTube video player" width="560"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Stuck on a mediocre bass sound?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hi there! back in 2009 I bought a precision bass kit from &lt;a href="https://www.thomann.com"&gt;Thomann&lt;/a&gt;, it was made by a then unknown brand called Harley Benton (!), it was way before they started selling complete instruments for very low price points.
Of course, they're a pretty popular brand as of today, but I guess you already know that...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;DIY bass package&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've checked the order confirmation email I got from Thomann and it seems I spent about 89 euros for mine. I checked on their website and I was able to track it down even today, it's now priced at 99 euros, and that's not too bad, less than the inflation rate anyway!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to try building your next bass, I suggest you give one of these kits a try, as this was such a good learning experience for me. Of course it's a pretty basic instrument, right now my biggest issue with it is that the pickups sound a bit muddy. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I went to Amazon to look for cheap alternatives to the onboard pickups. That's when I found out these &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/4nhMLZu"&gt;alnico V pickups by Artec&lt;/a&gt;, for the low low price of 27 euros, a deal that looks pretty juicy to me!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I was at it, I also decided to replace the pickup covers with these &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/3IbAEOP"&gt;cream colored ones&lt;/a&gt;, it's 6 euros more to shell out but I found it useful to better match the color theme of the bass, which is what makes it so lovely to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;A pleasant (sonic) surprise!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After replacing the pickups with the new ones I was pleased, these have more high end, a better low end and less muddines in the mids. I would call &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/4nhMLZu"&gt;these Artec pickups&lt;/a&gt; more modern sounding alternatives to the stock pickups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a bit of playing with the new pickups onboard, I've realized there's a new issue I didn't experience with the old ones... it happens when you accidentally touch the pole pieces when not touching the strings. It's an annoying buzzing noise that drives me crazy!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Ground those poles, ladies...&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a bit of research online, I finally figured it out, the Artec pickups sound nice but the manufacturer didn't bother to ground the actual pole pieces! I've learned that even Fender original pickups often have the same issue, and that's pretty crazy, if you ask me, especially if you pay premium price for these. Thankfully, that's absolutely not our case ;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luckily, &lt;strong&gt;the fix isn't hard to do,&lt;/strong&gt; you just have to apply some adhesive foil or metal strip to the back of the pickups, touching the exposed poles, then solder a wire from one coil to the other, and finally wire a jumper to the pickup grounds, takes about 20 minutes with a soldering iron.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's all for now, I hope you enjoyed my little test of the Artec Alnico V precision bass pickups, if you're the kind of person that subscribes to youtube channels, feel free to do so... or not! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's my &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/simmessa"&gt;Youtube channel link.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See you next time!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Music"/><category term="P-bass"/><category term="Bass pickups"/><category term="Upgrades"/><category term="Howto"/></entry><entry><title>Album review: Wim Roelants - Burn</title><link href="https://www.simonemessaggi.it/2007/06/en/album-review-wim-roelants-burn/" rel="alternate"/><published>2007-06-27T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2007-06-27T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>simmessa</name></author><id>tag:www.simonemessaggi.it,2007-06-27:/2007/06/en/album-review-wim-roelants-burn/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is an ancient album review I wrote in 2007: Wim Roelants - Burn&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wim is an established sessionman / studio guitar player in Belgium. Apart from being a performer, endorser, guitar instructor and clinician for many years, Wim is also a composer and songwriter, and "Burn" is his first solo CD …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is an ancient album review I wrote in 2007: Wim Roelants - Burn&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wim is an established sessionman / studio guitar player in Belgium. Apart from being a performer, endorser, guitar instructor and clinician for many years, Wim is also a composer and songwriter, and "Burn" is his first solo CD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The album is composed of 10 original tracks, the genre is instrumental guitar rock, with some blues/fusion accents and also a little bit of funkiness, which never hurts, if you ask me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first track, with its meditative tones, is quite an unusual way to start such a record, but the phrasing is interesting, as the jazzy chord progression drives its way to the end about 6 minutes later, with the help of a tight rythm section. I think it's a good resume of Wim's musical taste, but I found it a little unfocused, to say the least.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The title track, one of the album's best moments, has a catchy melody, and is a nice showcase of Wim's guitaristic prowess. the guitar works are well executed and overall solid. Wim sure is a talented guitar player and he's capable of many different styles. His soloing is pretty conventional though, it shows good feeling but it gets somewhat repetitive after some listening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The work of the other musicians involved in this project is truly first class, as it sounds inspired, like if the four have been playing together for a long time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shades, the 3rd track, with its slower pace and bluesy roots, is also quite enjoyable. I found that it benefits quite a lot by the inclusion of background acoustic guitars and the occasional funky rythm guitar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Quickening 2 intro brought to memory some of Steve Morse works with his band, the four musicians play tightly and there's room for some harmonic exploration as well as some true shredding moments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That said, I'm pleased to say that Wim is the kind of guitarist which is more after good melodies rather than the showcase of mad guitar skills. I personally like his kind of approach, cause the world's full of soulless notes-per-second machines and awful songs, and this is not the case with Wim.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all, the impression I received after repeated listenings of Burn is of a quite traditional guitar record. The production is about average, the kind of stuff you would expect from other guitar "solo" albums, and I guess this doesn't help much the "novelty factor". Maybe a less conventional approach could have made this record more enjoyable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bronze is another delicate, acoustic rock/fusion ballad, and like "in your eyes" it doesn't hurt, but it doesn't either add much to the overall character of the record.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Kickstart 2 oriental feeling is welcomed as a good change to the record's uniformity of style. The guitar's heavier sound leave a distinct mark but I found the bass the most convincing trait of this track. The soloing is, again, good but didn't strike me as particuarly original or new.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Karnak Karma, on the other hand, is maybe the most original of all the included tracks, with its ethnic character and the 2/4 drumming, I would say it's refreshing and therefore, a good variation of Wim's musical tone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To resume this album in a sentence, I would say "Burn" is a solid instrumental record with the predominance of softer, more melodic tracks. Even without truly excelling at anything in particular it's surely worth listening, especially if you're into melodic guitar works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wim cites Satriani, Steve Vai and John Petrucci as his main influences, but I found his style also very close to that of guitarist Andy Timmons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I you like this records I suggest that you check out also:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Tricot no pais das maravilhas" by Goncalo Pereira
Any record by Andy Timmons (Andy Timmons Band)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can check out Wim and his works &lt;a href="http://www.wimroelants.com/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Music"/><category term="Review"/><category term="Album"/></entry><entry><title>The Manowar 'epic' years</title><link href="https://www.simonemessaggi.it/2007/05/en/manowar-the-epic-years/" rel="alternate"/><published>2007-05-23T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2007-05-23T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>simmessa</name></author><id>tag:www.simonemessaggi.it,2007-05-23:/2007/05/en/manowar-the-epic-years/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;When I was a kid I used to be a huge Manowar fan for maybe 1 or two years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of my best friend got this Manowar double cd + videotape set which was very epic and fun (Hey Ace, how's it going?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I remember listening to "Hail to England" &amp;amp; "Into …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;When I was a kid I used to be a huge Manowar fan for maybe 1 or two years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of my best friend got this Manowar double cd + videotape set which was very epic and fun (Hey Ace, how's it going?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I remember listening to "Hail to England" &amp;amp; "Into glory ride" at least a thousand times. And I'm still doing so once in a while, with a different spirit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the very best part was the videotape, containing a sort of documentary of all things Manowar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've seen it many times and I used to remember all the hymns and slogans it contained, something very close to a religious cult.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I admit this "True Metal" thing is mostly bullshit but I recognize it was very fun at the time and I don't regret being a Manowar zealot, it didn't last much though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you feel nostalgic you can always chek the videotape I'm talking about, as some pious soul finally put it up on YouTube, the internet pulsating collective Memory / Soul.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's called &lt;strong&gt;Secret of Steel&lt;/strong&gt;, and it brought back so many memories!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="315" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/1JPfQd4Ap8A?si=8_Xvo-kntTZHWfCv" title="YouTube video player" width="560"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note from the future: This was some of the worst rock'n'roll sexist macho male stuff out there, totally unconceivable today, but it was so funny, I don't believe in these valors honestly, but please don't stigmatize / cancel this and learn from the past to make sense of the present and future times! Also, the youtube video might be gone or could be seen only on their damn platform, I didn't upload it and honestly I can't control it in any way, sorry.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Music"/><category term="Tutorial"/><category term="Email"/><category term="Hack"/></entry></feed>